e
for
e e
good evening everyone I'll Now call to
order this meeting of Committees of city
council for uh March 3rd
2025 we'll begin with a roll call of
members Mr Harris yes Madam president Mr
Med here Mr Royo here Mr C here M Greg
Miss Diaz here Mr hsh here president B
here councelor Craig is excused this
evening a few reminders for everyone in
attendance first please silence your
phones and devices if you haven't done
so already second this meeting and its
participant EV are being recorded
tonight we have meetings of Committees
of councel there are no general public
comment periods during this meeting
however committee chairs will call for
comments from the public on specific
agenda items comments are limited to
three minutes per speaker and must begin
with your name and block of residents
for our meeting record uh to keep time
we'll be using a light here it'll turn
green when a speaker begins turn yellow
when there's one minute remaining and uh
turn red when 3 minutes has been
expended thank you in advance for
allowing everyone equal time time now
we'll move to the approval of the
minutes for the February 3rd 2025
meetings of
committee so move second we have a
motion and a second for our meeting
minutes are there any Council comments
on the
minutes hearing none Mr Harris Mr Med I
Mr Royo I Mr Glee I Mr Diaz I Mr hirsh I
and president p i
all right our first committee this
evening is Personnel counselor CLE thank
you Madame President the Personnel
committee has uh two items on the agenda
for tonight the first item is the
nomination of Steven gr for appointment
to the city revitalization and
Improvement Zone Authority Mr G is
nominated due to his experience and a
perir request of Senator Scott Martin
due to his impressive legal background
leadership experience and dedication to
the linkter
community so now I'll make uh I think I
guess he's not here but oh could you
please step forward
please yes thank
you thank you very much sir thank you
very much thank you for your willingness
to Ser thank you for being here tonight
would you please introduce yourself and
uh tell us why you want to serve on the
board yeah sure well thank you very much
for uh inviting me this evening um I
have not actually been to a city council
meeting or a committee city council
meeting before so this is kind of my
first uh first
opportunity so I grew up in uh Lancaster
County graduate of Warwick High School
uh after law school I moved back uh
after a short clerkship in Altuna moved
back to Lancaster to start my legal
career I've had a law practice um here
across actually from the the courthouse
house for over 10 years I primarily do a
lot of litigation including criminal
defense and family law and some general
business matters um love Lancaster City
uh it's improved so much from when I was
a kid uh the only time I ever came
really to Lancaster City with my parents
we would shop and go to lunch at wton
chance uh and sometimes my dad would go
to um what used to be tmbb and he would
drag me along but it's incredible what's
happened to Lancaster City and a lot of
that's because we've had some great
leadership over the years love working
in Lancaster City serving the people all
over the county I I go outside of the
county too but primarily my practice is
focused in
Lancaster uh personally I live in manham
Township with my wife Melissa my son
Harrison and my daughter Olivia they go
to Manheim Township um I was on the
school board in Manheim Township for
about eight and a half years uh half of
that was either as president or vice
president but I stepped down last year
to just take some time eight and a half
years was a long time um I'm currently
on the board at UPMC I've been on the
board for about 15 years love that um I
think this board is very interesting to
me because it's completely different
than what I've ever done before um it's
very unique um I didn't know a lot about
it to be honest with you so I had to
obviously ask ask some people and do my
own research but it's really pretty
pretty incredible I love working on
boards I think it's a great Unity to
collaborate with other people uh to try
to find solutions to problems that we
may have and I'm just really looking
forward to getting started I think I
have to schedule an orientation uh the
next few days so I'm looking forward to
that uh but thanks again uh hopefully uh
the motion passes and I look forward to
meeting all of you uh in in the coming
days and weeks ahead and working with
you I don't if you have any questions at
all okay uh now I'll open up two qu four
questions from the other members of the
committee please coun
H I was actually pointed councelor met
although I just do want to say quickly
thank you for for your willingness to
serve uh thank you oh please on thank
you
coun uh thank you counselor colleagues
and thank you Mr Gage for taking our
questions uh and your willingness to
serve um how can we use uh crits to help
uh promote Economic Development uh and
Equitable Economic Development here in
the city well I think you've already
been doing it um you know like I said
just
the way that Lancaster City has changed
just in the last few years and certainly
over the last 10 or 15 years or 20 years
I mean it looks completely different
than when I grew up uh there's always a
new coffee shop opening up a new
restaurant opening up uh lots of
different services for people that uh
that need it here in Lancaster City
um and I think you know I think ler city
has become a place where people want to
do business cuz it's a good place to do
business and I think that we want to
keep that going and quite honestly um I
don't want to take any credit for
anything because I think that obviously
the good work has been done by those who
came before me and I just want to
continue to help Chris uh move forward
and certainly help the city uh as
they've been doing but uh they've
obviously been doing a great job thus
far
thank you for answering and that
concludes my questions Mr CL thank you C
are there any other questions or
comments from other members of
council and from the
public
sure do I have to say my name in Block
yes please okay Susie Gomez 100 block of
North Reservoir Street um are you
filling in the position on a legal
standpoint or are you filling in the
position on a board member standpoint
just board member position just a board
member yes okay thank you oh yeah
you thank you for your questions thank
you for your willingness to Ser sure
thank you thank you now I'll make a
motion to move discrimination to our
next full council meeting second all in
favors I the second item is the
nomination of Jessica Emy for
reappointment to the Board of Health
Jessica has been serving on the board
for 18 months just for the record she
completed the term of another Public
Health educator who retired and stepped
down from the board and she has
expressed her interest in continuing to
serve on the board are there any
questions or comments from members of
the
committee from
Council councelor CLE thank you um I
just wanted to thank Jessica for wanting
to continue to serve on this board it is
um active and we appreciate her
service thank you Madame President for
your
comment are there any other questions
comments now I'll make a motion to move
this nomination to our next council
meeting second all in
favors that concludes personal committee
Madam president thank you very much
councelor cleaks uh we'll next move to
our finance committee councelor Royo
thank you council president we have one
item on our agenda this evening it's
Administration bill number
1225 with is which is authorizing the
issuance of General obligation bonds uh
we had previously heard a presentation
from director Campbell on the uh list of
items that uh this Bond issuance uh
would be for I'd like to invite director
Campbell to the podium to talk about the
bill that's in front of us Dr
Campbell thank you good evening everyone
um yeah as I mentioned at the February
3rd city council committee meeting we're
introducing tonight an ordinance uh for
a 2025 General obligation Bond um in
February as councilor Royo uh stated we
provided you with a list of General
projects groupings that this Bond would
include um and attached to the ordinance
this evening is a more detailed list of
projects that will be included in this
Bond um I also brought paper copies
which I passed out earlier uh that might
be slightly easier to read and Daryl uh
P who's our Financial Consultant is
handing you some more information um
that he will provide some details on
later um when I'm through with my uh
initial comments
here um so in February I noted that this
Bond would consist of a proposed total
of 55.3 million in projects um this
number has gone down to approximately
38.4 million in financing for projects
um so I want to take a few minutes to
review the changes um I also just want
to note I don't think I mentioned this
in February we typically we typically
look at projects for a bond um that will
either be completed or nearly completed
within three years um so this funding
would mainly be spent over the next
three
years the bond consists of funding for
three of our funds so the general fund
as well as the water Enterprise fund and
the sewer or Wastewater Enterprise fund
the general fund uh has not changed
since the presentation in February so uh
19 million of this Bond around half of
it would be used towards projects that
are associated with the general fund the
projects themselves also haven't changed
um we've simply broken them down more in
the detailed list that we provided to
you um this evening and and with the
packet so there's still six main
categories of projects um and I'll just
run through those really quickly um one
would be implementing the parks plan uh
the parks master plan that was approved
for a variety of projects in a variety
of our Parks um our vision zero work is
another category uh the continued work
on our active Transportation plan um
maintenance to our facilities based on
our facilities conditions assessments um
and this grouping also includes a small
match that we needed to satisfy Grant
requirements for the welcome center
Renovations um another category is
upgrading our operations center for
better efficiencies and um then the
final category is just kind of general
public right ofwe upgrades so these
include uh traffic signal signals um
streets uh Street Scapes um and and that
type of
thing um moving to the Enterprise funds
then decreases were made in both the
sewer and water fund since our
presentation in February um I'll note
that these changes are not a result of
ultimately needing less debt financing
so rather we determined that we will
pursue pennvest financing for a couple
of projects based on the timing of the
projects and also uh pennvest loans have
significantly lower interest
costs um and and just to note pennvest
uh is a um is a state revolving Loan
Fund um and this is is a fund that can
only be used for specific projects um
mainly in water and sewer and some storm
water um uh projects as well so I'm
going to start with changes in the sewer
fund we are proposing 10.3 million in
financing in this in this Bond uh which
is down from about 18.7 million that we
proposed in
February uh we have three combined sewer
separation projects that we need to
complete and a portion of all th all
three of those projects have been
included in this fond um mostly for
design and Engineering work that pvest
will not support but the remaining we've
pulled out to pursue uh with pennvest at
a later date that financing will likely
not be pursued I'm looking at Molly
until 2026 um and we'll come back to
council when we're ready to pursue that
funding uh the general project bu
buckets for sewer do remain unchanged
from February so there's still a portion
of the funding as I just mentioned for
the combined sewer separation uh work on
our long-term control plan work to
design a new uh Anor robic
digestor um improvements expansion
Rehabilitation for some of our aging
collection system um emergency exro
escros to support projects uh that arise
in conjunction with our partners and a
camera truck uh which we discussed a bit
in February as
well um and then the last Enterprise
fund included in this bond is the water
fund so we're proposing B Bond financing
in this Bond of about 9.1 million this
has also G gone down from the February
estimate um which was approximately 17.6
million and this decrease is again due
to pursuing pen vest funds um I'm going
to talk a little bit more about this
decrease because it's all related to one
project which is the 42 diameter water
transmission main replacement we've
talked about this project often both in
financial aspects with capital planning
but also in numerous Public Works
reports um it's a very large project it
must be completed because the current
main is well past its usable life um and
this project will likely total about $41
million to complete we've received a $3
million grant for the project but the
rest of the project will need to be
financed so penbest requires that
projects be Shuffle ready before they
will loan funds so all the design
engineering permits Etc must be
completed and because of the timing for
the grant funds and some of the current
uncertainties for timing of procurement
of equipment um we had initially thought
that we would include some of this
project in the bond to ensure that we
would be able to start to order the
equipment and use the grant funds um
before we would be ready to get a loan
through through
pennvest however as we reviewed this
further and had further conversation
with pennvest we decided to pull that
funding out completely from the bond and
potentially pursue interim financing in
the next couple of months to cover these
costs pennvest will not refinance
permanent or Bond financing however
interim financing will allow us to move
all of the costs eventually into a
pennvest loan as they do allow interm
financing to be included once the loan
is actually ready to be dispersed this
will keep interest costs down very
significantly for us um and we'll make
interim financing well worth it uh to
save on that interest expense so I'm
saying all these details for two reasons
tonight um One is because because we
anticipate that we'll need this funding
for the water M uh over the next year
we're including this debt in the
projections that you'll see from Daryl
that he just handed out and he will talk
about in a few minutes because the debt
will affect basically the same operating
budgets as the bond we want to show them
at the same time um and two we will be
returning over the next couple of months
possibly even as early as next month
with with details of the debt of the
interim financing for you to review uh
as well
so that's really the the main changes in
the that's really the main change in the
water fund since February um there's
three other General categories water
quality improvements uh we need to do
some design work for the posos uh work
and Lead line replacement but those were
all on the previous list and those
groupings haven't
changed so I think I'm going to stop
there um and turn it over to Daryl to
provide some additional financial
information and talk about the debt
schedules a bit
thank you
Tina uh good afterno I'm sorry good
evening members of council uh thank you
for being let me be here tonight and
continue to work with you um the
presentation I handed out to you and is
uh will look similar for those of you
who might have been here about three
years ago when the last you know
multi-purpose financing was done so um
we're ultimately you're going to be
doing one what what what you call one
bond issue but we we we we try to tailor
each piece you have a general fund
component you have a sewer fund
component and you have a water fund
component so it's really kind of almost
three financings in one obviously you
economize on the on the related costs
but the key being hey you know we're
really kind of thinking about this and
we're also tailoring the terms and the
structures of each three component to to
best manage not of the use lives of the
respective projects um but also the
budgetary impacts so when we get to the
graphs a lot of some people like numbers
some people like graphs I think the
graphs pretty much show a pretty good
picture of kind of where you're going or
where you are and where you're going um
and I'll talk about timing then on on
the back end so if you join me on page
one this is what I'm talking about about
uh the general fund Pro I'm going to do
the high level of each fund and then I'm
going to go kind of vertical so the
general fund um is for the $19 million
of
projects um the sewer fund and that will
be over a term of 20 years again kind of
tailoring the useful life of the
respective projects uh the sewer
fund
um uh is is projects of about $10.3
million we're going to finance those
over a term of 30 years uh the Water
fund about $9.1 million and we're going
to finance that over a period of 25
years for a total projects of the 38
almost $ 38.5 million so now we're going
to talk each fund kind of
individually um so for the general fund
of the $19 million in projects uh we
start with where you are so that line
roow two there is the existing net Debt
Service for the respective funds so know
our current general fund Debt Service is
about $7.5 million with financing the
$19 million certainly you've already
adopted a budget for 2025 so we have no
no budgetary impact for the remainder of
2025 in any of the
funds um also just to allow time for
your for your obviously the projects to
be done and also to replenish some of
your reserves with with any of the
increases you've had recently or in 2025
we're not going to have any budgetary
impact in the general fund in
2026 um so you'll you'll remain at at
$7.5
million then the impact from this
borrowing in 202 27 will will be about
$900,000 so you'll settle in at about
8.4 million and there'll be no further
impact or increases uh in 2028 so the
overall budgetary impact of this
borrowing will be the $900,000 and then
when we get to the graphs you'll see how
it actually steps down in the future but
it'll never there's not another increase
coming is what I'm trying to say uh
sliding over to the Sewer fund the $10.3
million of projects your current
existing Debt Service is just under $4.7
million um in 2025 again for the
remainder of the Year there'll be no
budgetary impact um in 2026 even with
this borrowing your debt Service uh or
budgetary impact is going to be what
we'll call a modest
$120,000 because your existing Debt
Service is already dropping down okay
and and and we'll see that in the graph
uh and really there'll be no future
increases Beyond 2020 six so the overall
impact or budgetary impact of the sewer
borrowing is
$120,000 going go going forward and
again you'll see step Downs when we get
to the
graph water fund for the $9.1
million uh of projects your existing
2025 Debt Service is 14 million uh again
no increase in
2025 uh in line five there the
additional impact in
2026 this was a little bit different so
that
171,000 that you're seeing that's
actually was going to happen even if we
weren't borrowing another dollar today
so yes you're going to have a budgetary
impact or an increase in 2026 of about a
million dollars uh again all of that is
what was is already in your of projects
you've previously done and what's in
your current budget going forward um
then we're going to kind of take a year
off uh in
2027 and then 2028 as a function of this
bar borrowing the budgetary impact will
be that $938,000 so sum total uh of the
million dollar that or was there and the
$900,000 from this borrowing your
overall budgetary impact in 2028 will be
about $2
million I'm going to pause there uh
again I think the graphs are going to
show this much better but and so those
are the borrowings and the budgetary
impacts from this financing
any questions on that before
I Mr just one sorry uh one clarifying
question how were the um the years
determined for the term for each of the
funds it's a function of the useful
lives of the projects that there there
in the project list that you was handed
out there are useful lives of the
respective projects I kind of did like a
mathematical calculation to get kind of
an average life and we're being being
careful that you know this is like your
car you don't you don't you don't borrow
for your car for 10 years when you know
you're going to need a new car in five
so we're doing the same thing with with
the projects of you're financing we're
being careful that and and also it's
appropriateness you know you don't want
to while you don't want to finance
something longer if if you don't if you
don't need to why financing something
shorter and have a higher burden today
just to kind of save a lot more money
tomorrow it's it's not always Equitable
so we try to balance the terms of the
financing with the respective useful
lives of the projects being financed
okay councelor uh Mr P can you just
clarify So when you say impact this is
effectively the budgetary impact and so
far as like this is the interests and
other costs that are associated with the
financing itself it's the th those
yellow numbers that I'm that I'm
referring to as a budgetary impact those
are the increases in debt service so
going back currently have yeah on top of
what you currently have row two okay so
those are the that's the new that's the
additional annual expense on top of what
you already have and so far as like
interest expense expensing of the of the
issue in interest or well actually
interest and principal okay thank you
yep um so the the box at the top again
is the is the bond issue or the or the
budgetary impact a as Tina indicated uh
the Water transmission line is kind of
right around the corner if you will so
we wanted to you know kind of show you
what's right around the corner so for
the in the water fund only uh that water
transmission main that has a current
estimated cost of about 41 million I
just want to give you a snap shot and I
show it graphically again you know on
top of the bond issue being the top top
half that we're talking about uh the $41
million as a pvest loan which is what's
contemplated and
preferred um you're going to have those
additional amounts at the bottom in
2026 they'll be interest of about
476,000 in 2027 about
700,000 uh in 2028 you'll start paying
principal on that pvest loan so it'll be
at 1.8 million and in
2029 about 2.4 million just be clear
those are cumulative okay they're not
it's not 400 then another 700
okay um it may even be possible uh to
have that interest only be what's
referred to as capitalized and not have
a budgetary impact but kind of wanted to
show you more of a more of a worst case
presentation all right again some of you
like numbers some of you might like
graphs uh so on page
two
um is the uh before and after of general
fund the red bars being the existing
Debt Service going forward and the green
bar is being uh you know existing in
addition to the new borrowing so you
know like I showed you in the numbers uh
you're going to have no increase in
existing general fund Debt Service until
2027 uh that rise is that $900,000 I
showed you actually in a good way that
we're going to still step down or reduce
your debt service beginning in 2030 by
about $1.1 million why to provide future
capacity uh you know if if there are
additional projects that are going to
happen three four five years from now
this is providing that that budgetary
capacity to have additional borrowings
in the future then just like you seeing
the red bars already do that so we're
really kind of keeping that theme going
forward and that budg budgetary
flexibility uh then in
2035 uh de service is going to drop
another $1.4 million
um and then it's going to stay there at
that level until
2045 so overall when you look at these
graphs again you can tell say you know
we're we're extending your debt service
by two years from a year perspective
okay next page is the sewer fund same
concept um again for 2025 no increase uh
remember I told you that sewer debt
Services was going to increase about
$120,000 well the reason for that is
because as you can see the red bars
there's already a reduction you know
back to what I was saying about about
the general fund you know three four
five years from now you'll be
potentially adding Debt Service on a
lower base so you know you won't have as
much of a budgetary impact um then in
2035 uh your sewer fund Debt Service
that reduction will be about $900,000
uh again in
2043 about $500,000 is that reduction
and in
2049 uh that reduction is about $2.2
million again kind of getting back to
that equitability and why you financing
things earlier here you know we did
frankly stretch out the borrowing for 30
years because again it's more
appropriate given the useful life of the
projects being financed and again this
is providing flexibility and you know
certainly if you get there and you
didn't borrow any money by then you know
certainly you could prepay it at that
point but so it's really leaving the
flexibility for future
capacity lastly the water fund this
one's a little bit busier because of the
concept of the
pvest um so the red bars here are the
existing the green bars are the
resulting after this bond issue and then
the gold bars are layering over on top
yet again that 41 million the
contemplated $41 million pvest loan for
the water transmission line um you know
this this one doesn't this one as you
can see is already fairly level in debt
service so for the most part it's going
to continue to be level there are there
there are not step Downs in the future
um you know with with the useful life of
of these projects uh we're using a a
term of 25 years so again in 2026 that
first increase that million dollars you
you can see the red and the green are
the same because again that's already
that increase is already there uh
without this
borrowing um then the uh additional
increase from this borrowing in in in
2028 at $800,000 you saw from page one
and pretty pretty much stays there after
2048 and then would step down again to
fill out the 25 years and then the gold
bars again are just for even further
forward looking of layering on the
contemplated $41 million pen vest but
that is later for no not part of this
bond
issue
questions I have a
question
yes in regards to the dead service that
we currently have what is the complete
total of d
you want you mean sum total is that what
you
mean before or after
after looking here sorry give me a
moment I do not have it with the
existing can I get back to you I'm sorry
what if 400 million sound
correctly it's I I don't have oh I'm
sorry I do you do have it y
great no under that uh 3 370
million now I have a question which may
be
directed to Campbell and I mean
the since we're doing these projects
meaning that we don't for we really
don't know what's H what's going to
happen with all the federal regulations
in regards
to um construction materials but that
also possibly cause
a not being able to have enough and we'd
have to come back again and do another
Bond um loans
um yeah we uh have been looking at some
of the Federal Regulations um at this
point and um the the projects that we
have included in this we don't feel are
going to be um uh necessarily affected
by the federal reg regulations I will
say some of the design work that we're
doing might be um some changes but we
haven't put in for construction for
those projects at this point does that
am I saying that accurately enough
okay thank you so
much Council thank you Council Roy and
uh thank you for the presentation uh
this question is for director Campbell
um if you could talk a little bit about
the um budgetary impact and the
individual funds and how from a b from a
financial planning and you know uh
forecasting for the next 5 years how are
these budgetary impacts also being
looked at from a planning side yeah um
I'll I'll maybe take them as separate
Enterprise funds here a little bit so
for the general fund we have been um
doing some work with the multi-year
projections that we showed you with the
budget um just to ensure that we're
we're making sure that these are
included in those um so I mean obviously
it it affects the budget you can see
that in the in the paperwork but um it's
not uh we're we're not concerned at this
point about being able to um work with
it within the
um yeah the tax structure that we have
currently so we're not anticipating that
it would it would make us increase taxes
over the next five years um for the
sewer fund um we have been anticipating
that this is coming and so we have
raised rates um so we feel like we're in
in pretty good shape for the sewer fund
um and as you could see again with the
sewer fund um that um current the
current that uh financing is actually
going down a little bit and so we'll be
able to manage that one um pretty much
at the same level that we have been in
the sewer fund um for the water fund uh
we this is the one we've been looking at
the most um so we are in the process of
submitting a pu rate case um which would
um hopefully uh allow us to increase um
outside uh City rates um to help to
offset some of this work um we will
likely need to go back out for another
pu rate case in about three years and
that's the plan at this point um in
order to to work with that increase
again so that that's the the plan for
those
projections thank you and um with some
of the you know this big equipment that
we're buying we're also looking at the
life of the equipment and taking that
into consideration with the length of
financing as well correct yeah so um
Dale didn't talk about this but some of
the work that he did in the um kind of
amortization is really to stack some of
those so for example there's a couple
that are five years or 10 years those
are actually that financing is actually
um shown more at the beginning of the
the term so that it doesn't stretch out
as long thank you and that concludes my
questions thank you councelor any
questions from Council Council H thank
you uh councelor Ayo my question um
could perhaps go to either director
Campbell although though um it's just a
very general question and it
is some of the projects that are listed
in this I know
are are
are not maintenance but they're
extending the useful life of the assets
so they're almost like Rehabilitation
and not repair so to speak and then
there are also some projects um I'll
just use the design of the anerobic
digestor as an example where um and and
the the camera truck is another one of
these where will actually result in cost
savings to what extent does the city put
together analysis to understand how some
of these investments in the long term
will save on money not even necessarily
a return on investment analysis but is
there an understanding of how some of
these projects could save the city money
in the long run and what those savings
would
be do you want to speak to that
thank you very very much for the
question there's a lot of discussion
internally about what are the best ways
to not only build what materials to use
m means and methods which are
technically not the responsibility of
the designer but we talk about that a
lot because materials and methods go to
what it's going to cost to maintain or
operate the facility
sometimes that means looking at
equipment that is obsolete the VOR
machine for instance uh is is one where
which has a useful life of 20 years
that's an extraordinary amount of time
for this kind of equipment but it's
necessary to be able to cost effectively
maintain the infrastructure that we're
talking about in other cases we look at
the location of the infrastructure to be
built uh what properties need easements
what properties need to be acquired or
what kinds of construction methods are
required to to build that particular um
work so there's a lot a lot of often
cost benefit analysis in the nature of
the early discussions our Consultants
are are asked constantly is this the
best way to do this what are the not
only the capital cost implications but
the operations cost implications are we
going to have to hire more people to
take care of this particular
infrastructure in this particular way
or excuse me or can we maintain it
basically with the current staff but
with different equipment sometimes we're
making a decision about technology is it
technology that will not only maintain
or improve the water quality but is it
is it technology that will reduce the
cost of maintaining that there's a as a
municipal run utility there's a lot of
that kind of uh balancing that we're
that we often are doing because we don't
have the ability to go for the hot
hottest most expensive shiniest often
most efficient way of of doing it um we
don't have the ability to raise the
rates at the levels that the private
private utilities do and yet we are
required and are very proud of the fact
that we meet the same standards that all
the other utilities do so uh these are
constant
discussions most every one of our
discussions especially with the
consultants and when we're talking about
the sewer fund we're also sharing these
costs with several outside
municipalities and so they too query us
about are is this the best way to do it
the most effective way to do it the most
efficient way to do it the best
equipment to do it to what extent do
they have to be part of that solution to
what extent do can we reduce or delay or
phase the work in a different way that's
always an integral part of the
discussion
thank you director Campell it's good to
know that the other municipalities are
are looking to collaborate in that
way thank you director Campell actually
before before director Stephen Campbell
walks too far away sorry um I want to
kind of call back to something we've
been talking about the last couple of
years on Council and it relates to what
you were just mentioning as far as
planning goes but I just could you just
talk a little bit about the ways that we
have been um planning for like these
particular projects not just on this
list before us tonight or last month but
over the last several years because I
think that's an important piece of this
puzzle um is how we got to these
particular set of projects and why um
I'm very happy to talk a little bit
about about that type of discussion up
until relatively recently I would say up
until the last few years maybe three 3
to 5 years ago we often did our Capital
planning based on what was on the
immediate Horizon what we saw if we
walked around what we perceived as the
work that needed to be done or the
challenges that were directly in front
of us with when transite breaks for
instance it's cataclysmic it it doesn't
just break that line it often breaks in
Fair very a variety of places in the
same
neighborhood by developing a long-term
capital plan
where we can look up to 30 years ahead
in fact up to 32 years ahead it gives
gives us a lot of flexibility in terms
of what we need to do when we need to do
it and how what are the our options to
do it differently um the one of the key
I would argue and and Tina may say
differently but uh one of the key ways
that we were able to say that we can
reduce some of these costs in this
particular Bond at this particular
moment is because we had a longterm
enough Horizon to say this work has to
get done no later than 2040 or no later
than 2030 or something like that not
that it has to be done immediately or
that it has to be at a particular level
of
performance
um the capital planning effort not only
in terms of the the horizontal
infrastructure which is the water and
wastewater but the vertical
infrastructure which are our buildings
uh represented in our facility condition
assessments which is the work that we
completed about two years ago allows us
to say with some some level of
predictability it's not always perfect
and it's not always uh down to the day
or down to the month but one can say
that this particular asset the windows
in this building have a rem generally
speaking have a remaining useful life of
11 years and so at year 8 you need to be
planning to replace those windows rather
than looking the way we had before and
say I see a bunch of windows that are
broken do we need to replace all of the
windows yeah let's replace all the
windows that was expedient but not
planning
wise uh now we have that ability not
only in the vertical infrastructure but
in the hor horizontal infrastructure to
do that and we're going to continue
doing that one of the reasons to have
much of the camera equipment is to be
able to see internally to not only the
Wastewater lines but the water lines as
well what their conditions are and what
can be sealed what can be uh uh produ
done differently and cost effectively um
some of the SE some of the Linings that
we do for instance give us an additional
30 to 40 Years of useful life of some of
the infrastructure whereas previously we
might have had to think of just
replacing that infrastructure outright
so lining the infrastructure is
significantly less expensive to do and
gives us cost
effectively the level of performance we
we're looking
for thank you very much for that I
appreciate um kind of bringing that home
because we've we've been hearing about
this work of the capital planning and we
this is a direct result of that so I
appreciate it definitely can I just add
to that to um big thanks to Steve and
his team for the capital plan work
that's been done but also um this has
gone through as Steve suggested a number
of different iteration so it started
with a you know here's here's what we're
seeing as what we want and and me saying
here's what we feel like the budget can
handle and then kind of working uh to to
come to an agreement on that so and the
capital plan has helped us to do that
both very necessary components thank you
can I just make one quick correction to
councelor Diaz's question earlier um we
had said it was 372 million it's
actually 391 million so it was closer to
the to the number yeah that's the way I
calculated it I didn't know exactly
wow thank you director
Campbell thank you
counc I have I just have one question
when you plan all these projects do you
take into consideration unexpected risk
or challenges doing the execution of
those
projects um yeah I again will'll answer
for Steve and then he can correct me if
I'm wrong but there's always a
contingency included in the projects as
well as some um Rising costs so if the
if the project can't be completed in you
know the year that we anticipate then
there's also a a level of uh you know
increased costs that we're um figuring
in as well thank
you thank you
Council thank you director Campbell
director Campbell and Mr P for the
thorough presentations um any questions
from the
public sorry can I just mention one more
thing um we just want to talk through
the the timing a little bit on this so
this is an ordinance um we are planning
to um have the first reading obviously
um next week if if that is if it's moved
to that point um and then um hopefully
the second reading on March 25th um that
at least is the anticipated plan for the
for the auction do you want to talk
about that at all or
okay yeah so the timing from here would
be you know should you move move this
forward favorably to council the first
reading of the ordinance would be at the
March 11th meeting um and then we'd have
the bond auction uh and the second
reading or enactment of the ordinance at
the meeting on the 25th again that's the
goal if for some reason we were to get
slowed down for some reason um you know
certainly then we can just push that
back to the April 8th meeting so that's
the plan moving forward if we make the
schedule we're talking about we would
have closing towards the end of April so
you'd have the funds for the projects
then okay thank you for the
explanation well with that there's no
further questions from Council the
public uh I will move uh to send Bill
number 1225 to F Council on March 11th
for its first
reading I'll second that counselor Royo
um I'll be acting as a member of your
committee and Council Craig's absence
thank you council president I have a
motion in a second all those in favor I
that concludes the finance committee
council president thank you uh we'll now
move to Public Safety Committee
councilor Diaz
thank you president um the city of
Lancaster introduced a resolution number
18 2025 Which
authorized disposal of certain obsolete
police
records this action aligns with the
retention and the desos schedule for
records of Pennsylvania M
municipalities as the outline in the
municipal records manual the city has um
obviously
committed to
following of the schedule through the
resolution of number s in
1975 the resolution allows the police
Bureau Records Supervisor to dispose of
specific outdated records ensuring
compliance with the state guidelines for
the municipal record
management is there any questions from
the
committee uh okay any questions from
Full
councel any questions from the
public I have a question um do we know
how far
back at this time I did not time frame
wise specifically thises have there is
um I have a list
the list says some of them go back as
far as 2018 or as recent as 2021
depending on the category that they're
in and that's in line with the per
Municipal record
manual so do we know if um records will
be destroyed that has um counselors at
protests against the police officers
around 2020 so you said from 2018 the
earliest is 2018 on list the most recent
is I'm sorry
2022 there's a category of citations
animal complaints abandoned vehicles and
permits and related applications on this
list so Publix as well isn't
there public citations
meaning traffic and non-traffic it says
I beyond that I don't I can't speak to
specifics we weren't provided with the
specifics just a
list and they're asking those documents
be destroyed within a 5year
period not
20 this is the disposition schedule per
the municipal records manual uh that
Council Diaz
outlined thank
[Music]
you if there is no other questions I'd
like to move this to full Council on
March 11th second all in favor
ah and that concludes the Safety
Committee thank you Council Diaz we'll
move now to Public Works Council H thank
you council president uh the Public
Works committee does not have any
legislative uh items tonight however we
are receiving a presentation from the
public works department on uh trees for
people
so while they're getting the technology
set up I want to um thank you very much
for our opportunity to describe to you
the trees for people program it's an
initiative from um just before I got
here uh which culminated in a report in
2020 I believe and at that point we
hired a or shortly thereafter we hired
our first urban Forester who did some
great work with us for a while and then
unfortunately left we have since hired
another great Urban Forester who will be
giving this presentation to you um I'm
introducing to Molly dagger the if you
haven't met her before she's the deputy
director for sustainability and the en
and the environment which is where and
how the city of Lancaster fits in the
natural environment and she will
introduce Mike in
turn
sorry good evening held to members uh
I'm pleased to be here today to share
and updating you all as Dr Campbell
mentioned on Lancaster's urban forestry
program uh this is an effort that
continues to grow in both impact and
engagement at the heart of this work is
our new Urban Forester Mike Meyer who in
just six months has not only Advanced
the city's urban forestry initiatives
but has truly embraced laners community
and culture Guided by the 2020 trees for
people action plan the city's efforts
are expanding from securing funding for
hundreds of New Street trees this year
to navigating challenges such as the
suspension of federal
funding despite these hurdles our
commitment to a Greener more resilient
Lancaster remains strong driven by
Community Partnerships and a belief that
trees are essential infrastructure
improving air quality cooling
neighborhoods and enhancing overall
well-being this aligns with the broader
sustainability and environment Vision
which recognizes that Lancaster thrives
when its people and environment Thrive
together and with that I'd like to turn
it over to Dr Meyer who will walk you
through the latest program updates and
Community engagement efforts shap excuse
me shaping Lancaster's tree canopy
thank you for the introduction uh so as
a quick uh reintroduction to the trees
for people plan um this is uh the city's
plan for uh improving our Urban forest
and also making sure that everyone in
the city um no matter uh their location
or status uh has access to the benefits
of uh trees and that natural environment
um it's a really well done plan and it
says a lot about the city's passion for
its residents and the environment that
they put together such a wonderful plan
um most uh cities and municipalities
well maybe they have uh ordinances or
rules regulations that help try to
Foster uh more canopy um this plan truly
is very encompassing um and uh
definitely the Envy of of many other uh
municipalities uh we have been working
very hard uh to get external funds to
help support the mission of uh the trees
for people plan um I have a couple of
examples I want to go over real quick uh
we'll start with our uh USDA US Forest
Service this was a uh a very large Grant
of $1 million which would have at at
least planted 500 trees by 2028 but uh
that does even sort of of like while I
do love planting trees as Urban Forester
I I I I really like planting trees we
we're going to plant a bunch of trees
but um this also would have uh given us
support for you know pruning maintenance
these um all sorts of other additional
uh things that aren't just planting
trees because obviously trees have to go
somewhere improvements of those tree
Wells and such finding new tree Wells uh
and whatnot sadly this funding has
currently been suspended though um we
are ever so hopeful that it will come
back online so that we can get access to
it um however uh despite that we are
moving forward and onward as well now
for this summer we are very excited
because we have the urban Forest reset
project these are arpa funds through our
clean water Partners um and we're going
to be planting 376 Street trees
throughout the city um this is a a very
uh Hol istic uh Grant in that not only
are we removing uh stumps or filling in
um empty well sites with new trees but
we're also improving sidewalk and curb
that have been damaged previously by the
trees and the immediate vicinity uh of
the tree and as part of that we also
have um a public
facing front of this and I might
actually have to end my presentation for
a second
said again
I'm uh and so with a uh forward-facing
um app we have easy access for residents
to be able to go and take a look at all
of the various sites um uh that are we
are improving uh we can you know zoom in
we can you know you can search for an
address but also for every point it
tells you about the work that is going
to go on there um and so we're hoping to
expand on this uh we're possible um with
more info uh as the project goes
on uh additionally um for some general
program updates uh we are uh very
excited about the new Asset Management
program The City View City Works a dual
set there um being able to
multi-dimensionally track and account
for many of the tree related assets uh
of the city really opens up a lot of
interesting analyses uh so that we can
better um manage our system and uh more
easily and effectively um make changes
to our tree canopy and and other things
as well um we're hoping to do some
ordinance updates and um just today we
relaunched uh the trees website so it's
been nice uh and redone um which is a
just a big update from the previous
one uh and so some of just the
highlights here because uh you can all
take a look at it if you search for
trees on the city website uh we now have
a uh click it uh sorry I fix it uh link
right at the top there because that is
one of the most pressing issues Whenever
there is often someone's looking for
information on their tree it may very
well be because there's a branch down um
or whatnot um they'd like to come in and
report it they do a search this is
usually where it takes them so now we
can get even quicker access to that um
in addition to that we go over more of
our benefits of trees and um we are
really promoting our street tree
planting program um which helps
residents uh get new trees so that if a
tree does uh you know fall or have to be
removed um we can very quickly and more
readily replace those
trees uh additionally but off of that uh
we have been doing plenty of tree
plantings we had a large one in
cullington park last November which was
very successful was a very uh large
community event uh uh through our
partners at so we um there was music
there was dancing there was food and we
got to plant a bunch of trees I mean
that sounds like a good time um in
addition to that through this month
we're also starting uh some plantings uh
through various trainings or Community
Partners actually had a street tree
planting just this weekend um as part of
the new Lancaster County tree tenders
group so that's really great that was um
over by Bri side Church um through April
we're also going to be beginning the
plan for the urban reset Urban Forest
Reset Program um and so that will then
of course uh be a lot of improvement
through the city there um spring and
fall are our big times for that uh and
so we're excited about the the spring
planting um additionally uh we have been
growing Our Community Partners um most
of the photos that we have through this
uh I've tried to uh really highlight a
lot of the Community Partners we have
whether it be uh so we
or the alliance or or others throughout
that there's there's so many and they've
all been very helpful including numerous
uh neighborhood groups have started to
pop up um and so as we go through that
we're able to more and more better and
affect more effectively um communicate
with the public get them involved
because everyone needs to be involved
and have a buyin to uh you know this
very critical part of City
infrastructure um if you know you're
going to have a tree planted in front of
someone's house you want them to be very
happy about that tree because then
they'll be careful about it they'll care
for it especially until it gets big
enough that it can kind of care for
itself or at least big enough that then
it turns from I have to care for it to
now I'm worried about what's going on
with those branches which is where that
transition
happens uh as uh my closing slide I'd
say if anyone is interested in getting
involved um please reach out again um
one of the things that uh the trees for
people plan I think very uh uh
effectively uh says is that you know we
have these trees they are for people
they are for us we are a city filled
with people doing um their everyday
lives and um we need to make sure that
uh the resources the natural resources
around them are working for them um and
effectively uh and unless we have a lot
of community engagement um we're not
going to meet uh any of those goals and
so that is um one of the things we
strive for um and I hope we've been
doing uh fairly well so thank
you thank you all so much um honestly I
swell with pride when I see this
presentation it's it's a it's it's
wonderful in so many ways you know I
feel like I see Street trees as
something that if the city invests in in
the short term has huge long-term
benefits in so many different ways and
the fact that you all are engaging the
community in in it um I think that's it
gives all of us a sense of ownership
over our our city and I just think
that's really really wonderful so really
excellent work guys um I will open it up
to questions or comments from the public
works committee or full
Council Council pres thank you Council H
thank you for the presentation this
evening it's nice to meet you uh
officially um thank you just could you
speak a bit about I know that there are
probably some residents who have uh have
had bad experiences with Street trees in
the past and uh could you speak to ways
that this new plan addresses concerns
about what trees are planted in empty
Wells or replanted uh where there are
stumps and uh where trees may have
caused damage to sidewalks before yeah
so um I'm want to address that in kind
of two different ways uh the first one
is process uh especially since I started
I've been working with um you know
various people within the city to make
sure that uh we have a um a good and
effective process for addressing these
uh concerns like when a tree branch
comes down or when someone needs um to
have assistance um and I think we've
been working very well uh about that
we've made some significant improvements
in the last month or so in parts of that
um and so as especially as the city work
City View uh program come online that is
also going to make things much easier um
as it'll sort it'll very well streamline
things will be all electronic we won't
necessarily have to have people call in
or or maybe just through like the Fixit
link um so uh when it comes to making it
more readily available more intuitive to
get those resources um I think we're
going in the right direction um the
second part is uh more uh you know how
are we addressing you know our our where
our trees are placed and so um one of
the big things I always like to say is
more tree equal more better with the
caveat of the right tree in the right
spot um and uh one of the things that
I'm sure we all are aware of is that if
we're wandering through town uh the
sidewalk is not necessarily the most
level at times sadly that does have to
do with some of our trees um that also
is probably related to the fact that we
have nearly a quarter of the city trees
being Maples historically they've been
very easy to get and to plant but
because of how they work in their
ecosystem as some of the first ones in
there they put down shall Roots they
really grow them and push them out and
then of course the sidewalks kind of
suffer um that those sorts of decisions
you were at the time very much like we
need a tree we're going to put something
in there um we are being far more
systematic uh about that I actually just
redid our citing guidelines um to make
sure that when that we are either
planning a well or planning work around
a well we're keeping in mind now the
subsurface infrastructure more of those
clearances um and we are doing um more
to make sure that that tree that we put
there is the one that will work for the
the long you know the Long Haul um so
you know the really the best time to
plant any tree is like 20 or 30 years
ago but the second best time is now and
so we want to make sure that when we do
put those in in the next 20 or 30 years
people aren't wondering like what is
going on with this tree in a bad way we
wanted to be like what's going on with
this tree in a good
way thank you so
much any other question or comment from
councelor di in regards to um replacing
some of these trees do you have like
specific trees that you might have um
found that they're disease that neat
removal um is are there any issues I
mean I know one particular one that has
not been removed and it's causing um
especially when the wind
is really blustery it's it it actually
damaged someone's car and the
neighborhood is concerned so I'm curious
about
other you know what what exactly plans
you have to REM to remove these disease
um traits yeah so um uh with the uh
processes I talked about um we have
definitely made some improvements again
over the last couple months so that um
if we have someone with a tree that is
problematic we can more quickly address
it in the past we've not been as quick
at times uh for that um the City
Arborist and I have been working
together to make sure that when um we
identify a problematic tree um we are
now more quickly and aggressively
starting those next steps to either you
know address it if it's like an
emergency as an imminent Hazard or if it
is just hazardous which is in the
professional realm a different uh level
of uh of of Hazard um or something that
will fail in the long term like we're
we're working to make sure that we get
ahead of that more with community
members especially since uh for our size
municipality um every property owner is
responsible for the maintenance and
upkeep of the street trees and a
sidewalk in front of their property um
this is a piece of information that a
lot of people are not familiar with that
is part of our ongoing Outreach uh
efforts especially as the planting
season moves
on um really quick I think it might have
been a month ago and someone said that
they were going to go out there and
remove the tree and it's still there do
you know the length of time time does it
take um for that particular one that I
think uh you're referencing um we're
right now um just kind of moving through
the process it should be uh figured out
within the next month or so I will let
the um the residents now in that area
thank you thank you and if I can just
add one point to to your initial comment
counselor um one of the things that I've
observed that I really appreciate with
respect to the risk of disease and and
things like that is the intentionality
with respect to biodiversity and
really um it's beautiful to observe a
line of trees that are all the same but
then if that the same species but if
that particular tree species then become
susceptible to disease you're now
talking about eliminating a whole block
or having a whole block of trees become
at risk and so uh with s of this these
process improvements there's a real
intentionality to make sure that we're
diversifying the types of trees that are
all right for that particular instance
uh to be able to uh be more resilient is
there any type of metrics or studies or
any type of research that shows a
particular tree or trees in general that
have more susceptibility of becoming
disease I'm sure that there are
particular on but I'm I'm familiar only
with a few tread I'm
not I have allergies around this season
so trust me I stay inside um but I was
just curious about that that's a good
question I made some promises that I
wouldn't get too involved in talking
about the the tree inventory database
because I'm super excited about it um
but I will say that um we there are we
are very aware of certain species having
certain problems um it's a nature kind
of of things we of course have the uh
Ash uh trees which we've had some
problems with due to the emerald ash
bore um of course Dutch elm disease
affecting the Elms which is why we now
have a new variant that we've been
planting um but uh as uh to the earlier
question about like planting smarter I
have been growing and uh making our tree
database uh something that we can do
these assessments on like trees that we
know have these particular issues we can
do some spatial analyses uh another
reason I'm excited about having the new
Asset Management there is that um we can
then start to look at time um more so
than just kind of a like oh look this is
what we have at the moment um you know
I'd like to know like do honey locusts
do they start shedding branches when
they're like 15 years old um do cherry
trees really only last 30 years here
like are there issues with diseases on
trees that are just due to local issues
within the city uh that are just unique
to the city of Lancaster um so I would
like to utilize our data um just better
and more dynamically um so that we can't
address some of these things we can be
proactive on it we can say oh we have a
whole lot of these particular trees in
this area we now know that like if they
get to be this age or this size maybe
they have this problem we can start to
like oh let's go and keep an eye out
here do we need to do maybe some
maintenance or or talk to Residents
about these sorts of
concerns I just remember which tree I
really like the aliv tree oh but the
trimming on that tree is very once this
starts getting larger it's really hard
to maintain but thank you so much for
that information no
problem thank you Council Diaz any other
uh comment or question from
full
Council I'll also open it up uh if there
are any questions or comments from the
public uh how we're doing my name is
Jose 100
block of Coral
Street co-founder the West Crystal
volunteers
[Music]
the issues on the
trees very
good um at Crystal Park
between First
Street and Crystal Street there's a park
right there Crystal
Park
now whose responsibility is going to be
now to trim those streets and in all
those uh neighborhood
parks another thing
why we're planting how many trees
because we also do have other nonprofit
organizations doing the same thing
planting
trees okay uh how many trees we
need um we just eliminated I don't know
how many trees that were at least 200
years
old just to put a new park and to give
it an ey View but what they did was take
all the trees off what kind of I view is
that you just took the most important
thing out of that Park and that's behind
the Water Street Mission
ridiculous
uh the park where I'm at uh we take care
of that
Park the gentleman in right here in
front of me knows
that the you guys that come to pick uh
Park cleaning uh the only thing that got
guys have to do when they go to check
the park or clean it is just to take the
bag out of the garbage Camp cuz
everything else is is clean my kids
already took care of that for the past
six
years with still slow on maintenance in
that area it's taking
forever sometime it's because it takes
too long to get the part you need for it
in order this red tape I don't want to
hear the
rate that Park we have and every other
Park is very
important a safe zone for the kids and
that's what we're doing where we but
we're still missing a lot of items you
guys want to plant more trees we still
planting the water sew running water
that will go into the
ground we're still doing uh what for the
disabled they have our wheelchairs we
still doing the corners they're still
doing UGI I mean you guys
serious more
trees that's a waste of money so like I
say thank
you are there any other comments or
questions from the public
okay thank you so much that was
wonderful thank
[Music]
you thank you very much councelor H uh
we'll now move to our community planning
committee uh we're going to have councel
Royo chair that this evening and
councelor Craig's absence thank you
council president we have three items of
the agenda for this evening's Community
planning committee Administration
resolution number 2025
2022 excuse me 22 2025 and Bill number 2
2025 uh we'll start with Administration
resolution number 2025 amending the
sewage facilities plans to include the
558 Long Fellow Drive sub uh subdivision
um with that happy to invite uh Miss
Logan I believe is here and she can
speak to this uh resolution
good evening thank you um this
resolution is related to the sewage
facilities plan I'm sure you guys are
all familiar with having to pass these
um this project is
um making sure I have the
right one in of
me is for um a single s building that is
going to be turned into four Apartments
so right now it's a currently a um
vacant lot so there'll be they need to
have a switch planning module to add
those four units for
edus thank you um and yeah these are
regular occurrents at Council um thank
you for the explanation on that one um
any questions from Council or the
committee on this on this
resolution any from the
public great uh I will motion to move
resolution number
2025 excuse me 20
2025 uh to full Council March
11th second all those in favor I I thank
you uh and we'll move to the second item
on the agenda Administration resolution
number
22225 amending the sewage facilities
plans plan to include the 617 Fremont
Street
project thank you um this is for uh the
construction of three new single family
attached dwellings located at 617
Fremont
Street thank
you similar resolution uh as the first
item in expanding sewer capacity any
questions from the committee or full
Council from the public
great I will motion to move resolution
number 22 2025 to full Council on March
11 second all those in favor I
I thank you m thank
you third item on our agenda is
Administration bill number 2 2025
amending the zoning ordinance and
director dels is already at the podium
for this one director dels good evening
good evening everyone uh it's good to
see you um uh yes the action before you
tonight is related to an amendment of
The zoning ordinance it's a specific
Amendment uh related to Price Elementary
School uh you may remember um it was
last year that the council took action
on a property transfer related issue um
the uh the intent here is that um
there's a partnership happening between
the city of Lancaster uh the school
district of Lancaster and the Lancaster
Rec commission you may remember from the
property transfer action uh that the
main thing happening there is a portion
of sdo land um is being transferred to
the uh Lancaster Rec commission so the
the former Price Elementary School uh is
going to become a new Lancaster wreck
Center uh where they will offer
additional Recreation and child care
services in addition to that uh there
will be the construction of a new
Elementary School Price Elementary
School uh just to the north and that
will be on the land of the existing uh
Recreation Center so essentially what's
happening is there's a property transfer
and a land swap of of sorts one thing
that is uh important to note is that the
even though the school district of
Lancaster is going to be building a new
building is going be expanding its
footprint uh there are conditions and
requirements that all of the current
Brandon Park facilities and amenities
will uh remain in place uh and that
they're available to the community uh uh
for those par those Park
purposes so that's the backdrop I just
wanted to give you uh a little bit of
the history that we've already gone over
that ground the um the zoning amendment
that is before you tonight is to make
sure we're making the underlying uh land
use changes to support these uh these
property changes uh in particular there
is going to be an expansion of the parks
and open space zoning
district and uh in addition to that um
I'm sorry as part of that action there
is a map Amendment and a text Amendment
uh our plan is to provide uh a more
in-depth presentation to you all on uh
March 25th and then again again on April
8th as you may remember uh in the past
when we've done zoning ordinance
amendments it's a multi-step process
it's fairly involved um we have the two
readings uh we have an official hearing
we also in the background have uh public
notice requirements advertisement
requirements all of that good stuff so
uh the point tonight was really just to
introduce the legislative action uh to
Pro to provide the context uh for that
action and ultimately to let you know
that we're we're not really doing
anything at the next regular meeting on
March 11th but we are planning to
provide a presentation on March 25th as
I said and then again the hearing on
April 8th so uh if there are any
procedural questions I'm happy to answer
those about what's coming up the next
month uh or so also if there's anything
that you'd like to discuss related to
the the the backdrop or the context
happy happy to do that as
well thank you for the context director
dels um any questions from the committee
or full Council
Council thank you Council R thank you
director J for the uh um for your
remarks um with the timeline of the
project and does are is zoning ordinance
going to Hender the timeline of the
project or is it kind of aligned with
the timeline of the the
construction thank you that's a great
question um we actually have a a very
detailed project schedule that is
related ated to a number of these
components uh in addition to the zoning
Amendment for example there's also a
Land Development process that is uh
those approvals are required before
construction can start um as soon as we
are able to complete the zoning
Amendment step then the project will
continue through the Land Development
and the Planning
Commission your larger question about
the construction of the project we are
coordinating that closely with sdol um
and and they're aware of uh the
milestones in the
project thank and I close my question
thank you councelor man any
coun yeah um Director D just a quick
question um you said that there is a
hearing on April 8th that's taking place
at the zoning hearing board uh no we're
actually going to have that here uh at
Council okay so um we'll have to
coordinate that with you but the way
that we have done this before is we
usually open the hearing at the outset
of the regular um council meeting and
then after the hearing the hearing is
officially closed and then if the
counselers would like to have additional
question or additional dialogue that uh
um uh that is common and then you would
have the choice if you'd like to vote on
the matter that night on April 8th or um
wait until a later date thank you so
much thank you Council any additional
question Council colleagues thank you
counc thank you
for your remarks and
um how will the proposed amendment
benefit the community as a
whole thank you we've been working on
this uh for quite a while now the three
parties lanak SD and the city uh the the
main purpose here is ensuring that um we
are creating a holistic campus at this
particular site around Brandon Park so
that we're able to provide the park
amenities Recreation services and uh a
new school to serve uh the growing
Elementary School
population um if we design if we design
this well and we're able to make all of
these parts fit together properly then
uh we'll be able to achieve all those
goals in the same campus and we're we're
very excited about
that thank you thank you councilor deles
any additional questions or com from
Council from the
public thank you director del for the
context and background on the ordinance
yes uh much more to come thank you for
your uh patience I know you're going to
hear about this a couple more times in
the in the coming month or so so
appreciate the kickoff thanks with that
I will motion to move Administration
bill number
2225 to full Council on March 25th for
its first reading second again all those
in favor I I that concludes the
committee of community planning council
president thank you very much we'll now
move to Committee of the whole I have
two items on that agenda this evening uh
the first item is Administration
resolution number 19 of 2025 authorizing
the appointment of special Council for
collective bargaining uh director Tina
Campbell good evening again good evening
again um yeah so this resolution um is
to appoint a special Council for
collective bargaining um in consultation
with Barry hander our city solicitor uh
We've uh decided to engage a special
Council starting um this year to provide
legal councel in matters related to the
collective bargaining agreements um for
the city's labor negotiations with uh
with the unions particularly this year
with the asme Union because that's the
the contract that will be expiring at
the end of the year um we decided this
year to do this um there's been many
transitions in City Administration some
you know key leadership positions myself
included um as as well as the the home
RO Charter um and so we just felt it
necessary to have outside support for
the negotiations this year um so this is
to a point to appoint a special counsel
for that thank you very much do we have
a context of the cost for um uh
retaining special Council for a variety
of we do we we know that we do this for
a variety of reasons do you have an idea
of a cost cost of this um so I don't
have uh it it depends it's an hourly
rate so um the hourly rate for this is
about 365 an hour um we wouldn't be
using them for all of the negotiation
pieces uh but just to provide counsel so
just having them on retainer does not
cost us anything until we decide to use
them correct yes thank you uh other
comments from members of Council on the
resolution
councilor thank you council president
I'm just one question on uh where is
this budgeted to is this administrative
Services uh line item um it will be
partially administrative Services it
might also be some of the other
departments that are affected by by the
union negotiations as well
that thank you very much councelor
further questions or comments from
Council councelor Diaz can you repeat
that again the the cost sure it's 365 an
hour 365 hour is this is a temporary or
is this a full-time oh it's a very part
it's a very part-time um so it's just
when we when we need a council
negotiations correct yeah thank you
yeah any comments from the public on the
resolution hearing none I'll motion to
move resolution 19 to our next meeting
on March 11th second
Mr Harris if you would take a roll call
vote on this one
please yes Madam president Mr Med I Mr
Royal I Mr GLE i m Diaz I Mr HS I and
president B I thank you um and then
council members uh we also have
resolution 21 2025 on our committee of
the whole agenda this evening it's
recognizing women's history month we
typically bring this forward I'm proud
to introduce it again recognizing the
impact of women in the history of both
our nation and here at home in Lancaster
and women from all different backgrounds
as well um I'll be looking forward to
having some folks here hopefully at our
next meeting um for moving this forward
uh to celebrate them I'll have more
information at that time any Council
comments on the
resolution from the
public he non I'll motion to move uh
resolution uh 21 to our meeting on March
11th second again thank you uh Mr Harris
if you would Mr Med hi Mr Royo hi Mr
Glee i m Diaz I Mr h i and president B I
thank you members of council our last
item on the agenda this evening is the
clerk's report which Mr Harris have you
provided that in writing to all council
members I did Madam president thank you
very much
all right having reached the end of our
agenda I'll hear a motion to adjourn
motion to adjourn second again good all
those in favor I I you're adjourned I
just want to mention that today is
Puerto Rico Citi